Guide to the Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005 UA.90.F78
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Personal, Donald Goldstein, XI.
  - Consulting Film- Interviews - United States, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - Consulting Film- List of Potential Interviewees, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - Consulting Film- List of World War II Participants, undated (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - Consulting Film- Miscellaneous, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Consulting Film- Scripts and Revisions, 1990 - 1991 (Box 59, Folder 8-11)
  - Consulting-Arizona Memorial Orientation - Scripts and Related, 1990 - 1992 (Box 59, Folder 12-13)
  - Consulting-"Winning the Peace" Film Proposals, 1993 (Box 59, Folder 14)
  - Consulting-Tora, Tora, Tora: The Real Story of Pearl Harbor, 1999 - 2000 (Box 59, Folder 15-16)
  - Consulting-Pearl Harbor, 2001 (Box 59, Folder 17)
  - Consulting-"D-Day Invasion" - Interviews with European Participants, 1993 - 1994 (Box 59, Folder 18)
  - Consulting- Manuscript Contributions- East Inc, 1986 - 1987 (Box 59, Folder 19-20)
  - Consulting- Manuscript Contributions- Encyclopedia Articles, 1991 - 1996 (Box 59, Folder 21)
  - Consulting- Manuscript Contributions- Miscellaneous, 1981 - 2005 (Box 59, Folder 22)
  - Consulting- Manuscript Contributions- Schuler Manuscript, 1990s (Box 59, Folder 23)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- Correspondence, 1981 - 2003 (Box 59, Folder 24)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- Speech Notes and Outlines, undated (Box 60, Folder 1-2)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- December 7, 1941- A Retrospective, 1991 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- "Fight for New Guinea", 1992 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- "World War II: A Time Remembered - The War Fronts-The Home Fronts", 1993 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- "End of WWII, The Dropping of the Atomic Bomb: A 50 Year Perspective", 1995 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- Japanese Commanders, 2002 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- "The Bridge on the River Kwai- Death Railway", 2003 (Box 60, Folder 8-9)
  - Consulting- Speaking Engagements- "The Bridge on the River Kwai- Death Railway", 2004 (Box 60, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence- Goldstein and Prange, 1957 - 1980 (Box 60, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence- Holiday Greetings and Cards, 1974 - 1997 (Box 60, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence- Job Search, 1981 - 1985 (Box 60, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence- Miscellaneous, 1976 - 1997 (Box 60, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence- Post-Graduate Education and Early Teaching Positions, 1963 - 1974 (Box 60, Folder 16)
  - Education- Papers written by Goldstein, 1960s - 1972 (Box 60, Folder 17)
  - Education- Thesis, Masters - "Adolf Hitler, Administrator of a Society", 1963 (Box 60, Folder 18-19)
  - Education- University of Maryland Miscellaneous, 1950 - 1998 (Box 60, Folder 20)
  - Military Service with the U.S. Strike Command, 1962 - 1964 (Box 60, Folder 21)
  - Manuscripts- "Doolittle Raid", 2002 (Box 60, Folder 22)
  - Manuscripts- "Chinese National Interests and Military Capabilities: U.S./ China Relations in Northern Asia", 1979 (Box 60, Folder 23)
  - Manuscripts- "US Policy Concerning Renewal of Base Agreement with Philippines", 1988 - 1989 (Box 60, Folder 24-25)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 60, Folder 26)
  - Rembski, Stanislav, 1994 - 1995 (Box 60, Folder 27)
  - Resumes, 1970s - 2001 (Box 60, Folder 28)
  - Travel, 1979 - 1997 (Box 60, Folder 29)
- Course Materials, XII.
  This series dates from 1964 to 2004 and documents Goldstein's academic career from military institutions through his tenured position at the University of Pittsburgh. The majority of the files relates to his later positions and emphasizes his international relations and history courses. The materials included are further described in subseries content notes, 1. Military Institutions and 2. University of Pittsburgh.
  - Military Academies, 1.
    The subseries examines Goldstein's academic career at the United States Air Force Academy (USAFA) and subsequent institutions before obtaining a position at the University of Pittsburgh. He lectured on the United States, Western, and military history, and to a lesser extent international affairs and American minorities. The files are arranged alphabetically by course topic and then by record type. While the series includes a substantial collection of handwritten lecture outlines, the bulk of the series is reference materials. The reference materials generally include faculty manuals, readings, and supplementary texts that are arranged by course topic.
    - Administrative, 1965 - 1974 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies and Syllabi, 1964 - 1974 (Box 61, Folder 2-3)
    - Course Offerings, 1965, 1973 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - Evaluations by Students, 1969 - 1970 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Examinations, 1965 - 1971 (Box 61, Folder 6-7)
    - Extracurricular Activities, 1966 - 1970 (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Introductory Course Materials, 1969 - 1974 (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - Lecture Outlines- American Minorities, c. 1970 (Box 61, Folder 10)
    - Lecture Outlines- International Relations, c. 1970 (Box 61, Folder 11)
    - Lecture Outlines- Military History, c. 1970 (Box 61, Folder 12)
    - Lecture Outlines- Russian History, c. 1970 (Box 61, Folder 13)
    - Lecture Outlines- U.S. History, 1970 - 1971 (Box 61, Folder 14-18)
    - Lecture Outlines- Western History, c. 1970 (Box 61, Folder 19-21)
    - Lecture Outlines- World History/ Miscellaneous, c. 1970 (Box 61, Folder 22)
    - Reference Materials
      - American Minorities, 1964 - 1973 (Box 62, Folder 1-7)
      - Bases of Power and Conflict Series, 1971 (Box 62, Folder 8)
      - China Background and Communism, 1966 - 1970 (Box 62, Folder 9)
      - Command and Management Readings, 1972 - 1975 (Box 62, Folder 10-13)
      - Communication and Speaking, 1963 - 1968 (Box 62, Folder 14)
      - Diplomatic History, 1962 - 1963 (Box 62, Folder 15)
      - Far Eastern History, c. 1970 (Box 62, Folder 16)
      - How to in the Military, 1966 - 1972 (Box 62, Folder 17)
      - Military Environment, 1972 (Box 62, Folder 18)
      - Military History, 1965 - 1971 (Box 63, Folder 1-3)
      - Miscellaneous, c. 1967 (Box 63, Folder 4)
      - Modern Warfare, 1967, 1972 (Box 63, Folder 5-8)
      - National Security, 1964 (Box 63, Folder 9)
      - Russian / Soviet History, 1970 - 1972 (Box 63, Folder 10)
      - Soviet Arms Control, 1970 (Box 63, Folder 11)
      - U.N.. Peace Keeping Forces, 1965 (Box 63, Folder 12)
      - USAF Doctrine, 1955 - 1971 (Box 63, Folder 13 - 16)
      - US History, 1965 - 1967 (Box 63, Folder 17-18)
      - Western History, 1967 - 1969 (Box 63, Folder 19-21)
      - World History, 1961, 1968 (Box 63, Folder 22)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 2.
    The subseries details Goldstein's academic career at the University of Pittsburgh (Pitt), from his initial position with the Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corp (AFROTC) through his professorships with the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA) and the Honors College. More information can be obtained in the following subsections: Administrative Files and Course Materials
    - Administrative
      Scope and Contents note
      The subsection is comprised of records amassed by Goldstein while fulfilling departmental duties and serving the community. His professional advancement can be traced through the GSPIA memoranda, Pitt correspondence, and recommendations files. The GSPIA curriculum files provide an inclusive view of strategic plans and classes proposals for the department. The speaking engagement file highlights Goldstein's contributions to the public, specifically his presentations to community organizations. Researchers interested in a characteristic sample of Goldstein's course materials should review the Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching Award Dossier files.
      - Book Proposals, c. 1980 - 1990 (Box 64, Folder 1)
      - Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching Award- Dossier, 1994 (Box 64, Folder 2-6)
      - Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching Award- Miscellaneous, 1986 - 2002 (Box 64, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence- General, 1975 - 2002 (Box 64, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence- Speaking Engagements, 1975 - 2002 (Box 64, Folder 9-10)
      - Deposition for McKinney vs. University of Pittsburgh, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 11)
      - Ephemera, 1977 - 2005 (Box 64, Folder 12)
      - Exercises Presidential Management Internship, 1978 - 2001 (Box 64, Folder 13)
      - GSPIA Budget and Curriculum, 1968 - 2000 (Box 64, Folder 14-15)
      - GSPIA Memoranda, 1977 - 2002 (Box 64, Folder 16-17)
      - GSPIA Strategic Plan, 1997 - 1999 (Box 64, Folder 18)
      - International Relations Committee Historical Series Project, 1978 - 1987 (Box 64, Folder 19)
      - Letters of Recommendation and Thanks, 1975 - 2000 (Box 64, Folder 20)
      - Study of International Affairs Programs, 1987 (Box 64, Folder 21)
    - Course Materials
      This subsection is arranged alphabetically by course topic. The Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corp (AFROTC) courses address the requirements of the academic program. The History courses examine U.S. diplomatic history. The International Affairs courses explore the basic concepts of international affairs and application of international economic and social policies. The International Security courses cover the basic concepts, vocabulary, and analytical methods of international security studies. The Model Organization of American States (MOAS) courses prepare students for a mock session of the OAS General Assembly. The Policy Analysis courses analyze the formulation, implementation, and evaluation of public policies. The Ridgway Center files describe the activities of The Center for Arms Control and International Security Studies, which was rededicated in 1988 as The Matthew B. Ridgway Center for International Security Studies. U.S. Military Action courses examine the history and impact of wars waged by the United States from the American Revolution to Desert Storm. Each course topic combines materials from related courses, and consists of syllabi, bibliographies, examinations, quizzes, lecture outline, assignments, exercises, reference materials, and student evaluations.
      - Air Force ROTC- Administrative, 1974 - 1977 (Box 65, Folder 1)
      - Air Force ROTC- Course Materials and Ephemera, 1976 - 1977 (Box 65, Folder 2)
      - Air Force ROTC- Lessons, 1971 - 1973 (Box 65, Folder 3)
      - Air Force ROTC- Reference Materials, 1970 - 1977 (Box 65, Folder 4-10)
      - History- Course Materials, 1988 - 2001 (Box 65, Folder 11)
      - History- Course Packets, 1991 (Box 65, Folder 12)
      - History- Evaluations by Students, 1991 - 2004 (Box 65, Folder 13 - 15)
      - History- Lecture Notes, undated (Box 65, Folder 16)
      - History- Reference Materials, undated (Box 65, Folder 17)
      - International Affairs- Course Materials, 1988 - 2001 (Box 65, Folder 18-19)
      - International Affairs- Course Packets, 1991 (Box 65, Folder 20-21)
      - International Affairs- Evaluations by Students, 1994 - 2002 (Box 65, Folder 22)
      - International Affairs- Reference Materials, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 23-24)
      - International Security- Course Materials, 1974 - 2001 (Box 66, Folder 1-3)
      - International Security- Course Proposal, 1979 (Box 66, Folder 4)
      - International Security- Evaluations by Students, 1994 - 2002 (Box 66, Folder 5-8)
      - International Security- Reference Materials, 1972 - 1999 (Box 66, Folder 9-17)
      - Model Organization of American States- Antigua and Barbuda, 1995 - 1996 (Box 67, Folder 1-2)
      - Model Organization of American States- Bolivia, 1996 - 1997 (Box 67, Folder 3-4)
      - Model Organization of American States- Honduras, 1997 - 1998 (Box 67, Folder 5-7)
      - Model Organization of American States- Canada, 1998 - 2001 (Box 67, Folder 8-12)
      - Model Organization of American States- Mexico, 2001 - 2002 (Box 67, Folder 13)
      - Policy- Course Materials, 1971 - 1997 (Box 67, Folder 14-15)
      - Policy- Course Packets, undated (Box 67, Folder 16)
      - Policy- Evaluations by Students, 1981 - 1997 (Box 68, Folder 1-2)
      - Policy- Exercises, 1976 - 2002 (Box 68, Folder 3)
      - Ridgway Center- 40th Anniversary of Korean War, 1988 - 1990 (Box 68, Folder 4-5)
      - Ridgway Center- 50th Anniversary of Korean War, 2000 (Box 68, Folder 6)
      - Ridgway Center- Administrative Documents, 1975 - 2002 (Box 68, Folder 7)
      - Ridgway Center- Ephemera, 1988 - 2002 (Box 68, Folder 8)
      - Ridgway Center- Other Lectures, 1988 - 1990 (Box 68, Folder 9)
      - Ridgway Center- Papers on Pacific Security, 1986 - 1993 (Box 68, Folder 10-11)
      - Ridgway Center- Programs and Publications, 1975 - 1999 (Box 68, Folder 12)
      - Semester at Sea- Activities, 1993 (Box 68, Folder 13)
      - Semester at Sea- Administrative Files, 1993 (Box 68, Folder 14)
      - Semester at Sea- Course Materials, 1993 (Box 68, Folder 15 - 18)
      - Semester at Sea- Lecture Notes, 1993 (Box 69, Folder 1)
      - Semester at Sea- Newsletters, 1993 (Box 69, Folder 2)
      - Semester at Sea- Text and Reader, 1992 (Box 69, Folder 3)
      - United States Military Action- Course Materials, 1976 - 2001 (Box 69, Folder 4)
      - United States Military Action- Course Packets, 1992 (Box 69, Folder 5)
      - United States Military Action- Evaluations by Students, 1996 - 2004 (Box 69, Folder 6-8)
      - Reference Materials- Civil War, undated (Box 69, Folder 9)
      - Reference Materials- Grenada, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 10)
      - Reference Materials- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 69, Folder 11)
      - Reference Materials- Modern Warfare, 1956 - 2002 (Box 69, Folder 12)
      - Reference Materials- New American Way of War, 1979 (Box 69, Folder 13)
- Photographs, XIII.
  This series contains images removed from the first twelve series for preservation purposes. Most of the files relate to World War II and consist of original photographs, reprints, negatives, illustrations, and photocopied images. The items are further described in the following subseries: Non World War II and World War II.
  - Non World War II, 1.
    With the exception of the personal photographs, the images in this subseries are directly tied to the research and publication of books by Gordon Prange and Donald Goldstein. The arrangement in this subseries reflects the overall collection arrangement, which is alphabetically by research topic. Under each topic, the photographs are separated into published and unpublished images. The published images are arranged exactly as they appear in the book and are followed by the unpublished images. Generally speaking, the unpublished images were considered for publication, but ultimately rejected. One especially enlightening collection of photographs is the scrapbook created by Lieutenant General Chung Il Kwon, ROK Army, which provides a soldier's perspective of the Korean War.
    - Earhart
      - Published Images, c. 1920 - 1937 (Box Photo 1, Folder 1)
        - Route of Amelia Earhart's last flight, May 21 to July 1937; map., 1.
          Missing Title
          Page number: Inside front cover
          Photo number: 1
        - No caption, 2.
          Photo number: 2
        - Sear area of Itasca, July 2 through July 16, 1937; map., 3.
          Photo number: 3
        - A young Amelia with her mother, Amy, during the 1920s - before her days as an aviatrix., 4.
          Page number: P1
          Photo number: 4
        - Amelia in her flight suit before the famous 1929 Friendship flight, when she became the first woman to fly across the Atlantic., 5.
          Page number: P2
          Photo number: 5
        - The Friendship arrives in Southampton, England, after landing at Burry Port, Wales, following the flight from Newfoundland., 6.
          The plane was a Fokker F-7 originally flown by the explorer Richard E. Byrd.
          Photo number: 6
        - Amelia and Captain A. H. White after a June 1928 flight from Croydon to Northolt, England., 7.
          Page number: P3
          Photo number: 7
        - Amelia with Orville Wright (left of plaque) and Senator Bingham (right) at the Wright Memorial in Kitty Hawk, North Carolina, in December 1928., 8.
          Photo number: 8
        - With Bill Stultz, who piloted the Friendship across the Atlantic, in June 1928., 9.
          Stultz would die a year later in a crash at Roosevelt Field, New York.
          Page number: P4
          Photo number: 9
        - At home with her husband George Putnam, Amelia's promoter and a well-known publisher., 10.
          Photo number: 10
        - Amelia with famous aviatrix Ruth Nichols., 11.
          Page number: P5
          Photo number: 11
        - With polar flier Bernt Balchen in front of their plane in Teterboro, New Jersey., 12.
          Balchen outfitted Amelia's Lockheed Vega for her solo crossing of the Atlantic.
          Photo number: 12
        - Arriving at Culmore Field in Northern Ireland after her transatlantic solo flight in May 1932., 13.
          Amelia had proved her skills as a pilot and gained even more fame.
          Page number: P6
          Photo number: 13
        - Leaving Buckingham Palace after a visit with the Prince of Wales., 14.
          Photo number: 14
        - Greeted by Andrew Mellon, the American ambassador to Great Britain, upon her arrival in London on May 22., 15.
          Page number: P7
          Photo number: 15
        - A triumphant Amelia waves to the New York crowd during a parade celebrating her transatlantic flight., 16.
          Photo number: 16
        - Amelia and her husband in flight suits, January 1935., 17.
          Page number: P8
          Photo number: 17
        - With famous aviator Wiley Post in Cleveland, March 1935., 18.
          Post and Will Rogers died in a crash in Alaska during an attempt to fly around the Arctic Circle.
          Page number: P9
          Photo number: 18
        - Emerging from her plane on arrival in Oakland after her January 1935 flight from Honolulu., 19.
          Amelia was the first person ever to make this solo trip.
          Photo number: 19
        - Reporters interview Amelia with her husband at her side in front of an enthusiastic crowd at Newark Airport., 20.
          Page number: P10
          Photo number: 20
        - Greeted by a Mexican official at Newark Airport after her successful flight from Mexico City in May 1935., 21.
          Photo number: 21
        - Standing beside her Vega at March Field, California, 1936., 22.
          This plane was replaced by the "Flying Laboratory," the Lockheed Electra 10E, later in the year.
          Page number: P11
          Photo number: 22
        - With Edward C. Elliot, the president of Purdue University, holding a model of her "Flying Laboratory," then under construction., 23.
          Page number: P12
          Photo number: 23
        - Watching mechanics repair her Electra in Burbank, California, after her 1937 crash in Honolulu., 24.
          Photo number: 24
        - Amelia and her husband study the route she plans to take on her around-the-world flight in 1937., 25.
          Page number: P13
          Photo number: 25
        - Preparing two distress signals before her attempt to fly around the world., 26.
          Photo number: 26
        - Amelia prior to her final flight., 27.
          From left are: George Putnam, Amelia, Harry Manning, and Bo McKneely, a mechanic at Union Air Terminal in Los Angeles. Manning, originally scheduled to be Amelia's navigator, had to return to his ship after the trip was delayed.
          Photo number: 27
        - Amelia and navigator Fred Noonan in San Juan, Puerto Rico, where they finished a leg of their flight., 28.
          Page number: P14
          Photo number: 28
        - The pilot with her navigator and Vicomte Jacques de Sibour, who had helped to arrange the flight, in Karachi., 29.
          Photo number: 29
        - Amelia, a well-rounded person, enjoyed tending the garden at her Rye, New York, home., 30.
          Page number: P15
          Photo number: 30
        - Amelia in the place she loved best, the cockpit of her plane., 31.
          Photo number: 31
        - no caption, 32.
          Page number: P16
          Photo number: 32
      - Extras, c. 1928 - 1937 (Box Photo 1, Folder 2-3)
    - International Relations
      - Dictionary of Twentieth Century World Politics- Published Images, 1890 - 1990 (Box Photo 1, Folder 4-6)
      - Dictionary of Twentieth Century World Politics- Extras, 1917 - 1990 (Box Photo 1, Folder 7-11)
      - HarperCollins Dictionary- Published Images, 1754 - 1992 (Box Photo 1, Folder 12-13)
      - HarperCollins Dictionary- Extras, c. 1870 - 1995 (Box Photo 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Korean War
      - Published Images, 1939 - 1950 (Box Photo 1, Folder 16-19)
        - Cpl. George D. Smedley of Mount Vernon, Indiana, and Sgt. Thomas P. Montana of Yuma, Arizona, 1st Cavalry Division keep watch along the 38th Parallel. RG6S-KWP.36 (SC 350615); See photo 6-1., 1.
          Page number: Front Cover
        - Fifty-caliber ammunition being loaded into an F-51 Mustang at an airfield in South Korea. RG6S-KWP.1352; See photo 3-15., 2.
          Page number: Title Page
        - "Land of Morning Calm", 3.
          Page number: 1
          Photo number: 1-1
        - American soldiers removing boulders to permit motorized vehicles to ford a stream. RG6S-KWP.2193 (SC 344021), 4.
          Photo number: 1-2
        - Men of the 9th Infantry Regiment advancing up Hill 201. RG6S-KWP.2205 (SC 348664) OR RG6S-KWP.72 (SC 348664), 5.
          Photo number: 1-3
        - Soldiers navigating rough terrain., 6.
          Page number: 2
          Photo number: 1-4
        - The rugged terrain of Korea., 7.
          Photo number: 1-5
        - The unforgiving Korean winter., 8.
          Photo number: 1-6
        - The battleship USS Wisconsin patrolling Korean waters., 9.
          Page number: 4
          Photo number: 1-7
        - Buddhist shrine., 10.
          Photo number: 1-8
        - Father Charles Meeus saying Mass for Korean children., 11.
          Photo number: 1-9
        - Paddy field in built-up area., 12.
          Page number: 5
          Photo number: 1-10
        - Farmer and his primitive ox-drawn cart., 13.
          The banner in the background is in Japanese, which illustrates the remaining Japanese influence in Korea.
          Photo number: 1-11
        - Farmer on unpaved thoroughfare., 14.
          Photo number: 1-12
        - Typical Korean home., 15.
          Photo number: 1-13
        - Historic pagoda., 16.
          Page number: 7
          Photo number: 1-14
        - South gate of Seoul., 17.
          Photo number: 1-15
        - Statue of Adm. Yi Sun-sin, Korean naval hero., 18.
          Page number: 8
          Photo number: 1-16
        - Shinto shrine where students studied., 19.
          Photo number: 1-17
        - Two outlets of underground petroleum tanks built by the Japanese to refuel their battleships during World War II. RG6S-KWP.632 (SC 309926), 20.
          Page number: 9
          Photo number: 1-18
        - Franklin D. Roosevelt of the United States, Ismet Inonu of Turkey, and Winston Churchill of Great Britain, at the 1943 Cairo conference. 49-13193, 21.
          Photo number: 1-19
        - Gen. Douglas MacArthur with his trademark, a corncob pipe., 22.
          Page number: 10
          Photo number: 1-20
        - Meeting in Seoul between U.S. and USSR commissions in March 1946, 23.
          (Seated, left to right, Lt. Gen. John R. Hodge, Col. General D. F. Stikoff, and Maj. Gen. N. G. Lebedoff). 52-10148
          Photo number: 1-21
        - The Military Armistice Commission in 1947., 24.